Guide to the Brooklyn schools collection CBHM.0006
Center for Brooklyn History
Brooklyn schools collection
1828-2023
Center for Brooklyn History
CBHM.0006
92 Linear Feet in 19 boxes, two flat file folders, and 21 shelves of yearbooks.
The Brooklyn schools collection consists of materials relating to Brooklyn schools, both public and private, ranging from nursery schools to post-graduate institutions. Schools that are more robustly represented in the collection include Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Brooklyn Technical High School, and St. John's University.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was formally accessioned in 1985. Sources and dates of acquisition for the bulk of materials is unknown. PS 139 Class of 1917 photograph gift of Lynn Washbourne Williams, 2011. Erasmus Hall High School class of 1932 photograph is the gift of Roy Nydorf, Ethan Nydorf, and Amy Moore, in loving memory of their father Seymour Nydorf, 2017. Girl's High School yearbook (1947) is the gift of Linda Chelmow, 2017. New materials will continue to be added to this collection as they are acquired.
Historical note
In colonial New York, young people primarily received education through private schoolmasters and tutors, and free schooling was available to poor families through the Dutch Reformed and Catholic churches. Following the establishment of a state government, the Regents of the University of the State of New York granted charters for secondary schools in the state; the first charter, in 1768, was for Erasmus Hall Academy, located in the present-day Brooklyn neighborhood of Flatbush. Individual school districts in Kings County were created based on village, town, or neighborhood boundaries, with each district receiving funding from local taxes, state contributions, and student tuition. This system continued into the mid-19th century, when Brooklyn created a municipal board of education in 1843 to oversee all schools in the city.
While the number of schools in Brooklyn grew, very few educational opportunities existed beyond the primary grades for the children of poor or working class parents. Secondary schools such as Erasmus Hall and the Brooklyn Female Academy (opened in 1846, and now known as the Packer Collegiate Institute) were private, and therefore only affordable for middle class and wealthy families. The Central Grammar School, founded in 1878, was the first public school in Brooklyn to offer secondary level classes. Out of Central Grammar School, Boys' High School and Girls' High School, the first public high schools in Brooklyn, were formed to meet the demand and need for free public education beyond elementary school. Higher education also became available in Brooklyn around this time, as the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute (now known as Polytechnic Institute of New York University) conferred its first baccalaureate degrees in 1871, and St. Francis Academy evolved from a monastery and preparatory school to St. Francis College in 1885. Black children in Brooklyn attended separate schools until the 1880s, and the last school in New York City to be explicitly racially segregated was closed in 1900.
New York City consolidated in 1898. Immigration caused the student population to surge and during the 1950s the city's public school system enrolled more than a million students. Residential segregation led to racial segregation in schools and poor outcomes in poor neighborhoods and among students of color. In the 1960s, parents and residents began demanding change, including an especially acrimonious conflict in the Ocean Hill-Brownsville area in 1968. The school decentralization law of 1970 relieved these tensions, assigning governance of elementary and junior high schools to community boards, while high schools remained under the control of the Board of Education. National movements to provide bilingual education and special needs education came to New York City schools in the 1970s, but the city's public schools nonetheless still faced many shortcomings into the 1990s. In 2002, Mayor Michael Bloomberg successfully advocated to have control of the New York City school system transferred to the mayor. In the 2020s, the New York City public school system remains plagued by funding cuts and de facto segregation.
Sources
Lopate, Carol. Education and Culture in Brooklyn: A History of Ten Institutions. Brooklyn, N.Y.: Brooklyn Education and Cultural Alliance, 1979.
Ment, David. "Public schools." In Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, 955-961. New Haven: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Related Materials
Class photograph collection (BCMS.0029)
Brooklyn High School Newspaper Collection (BCMS.0030)
The Packer Collegiate Institute records (2014.019)
Erasmus Hall Academy records (ARC.230)
Pratt Institute collection (1985.056)
Girls' High School collection (ARC.128)
Boys' High School register and publications (ARC.123)
Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute collection (1985.055)
Adelphi Academy collection (1985.059)
Boys' High School and PS 247 class photographs (2002.020)
Bella Gordon P.S. 64 Collection (BCMS.0042)
Group portrait photographs of classes at P.S. 139 in Flatbush (V1992.006)
PS 143 Class Book (2012.013)
Virginia W. Warthin collection (ARC.319)
School composition books and diaries collection (1977.348)
Old Crowd of Brooklyn Public School No. 3 reunion collection (1978.118)
Bretz family papers (ARC.321)
Yeshivah of Flatbush High School yearbooks are available on the digital collections as a part of the Brooklyn Jewish History Project (BJHP)
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn schools collection consists of materials relating to Brooklyn schools, both public and private, ranging from nursery schools to post-graduate institutions. Schools that are more robustly represented in the collection include Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Brooklyn Technical High School, and St. John's University. Materials in the collection include school catalogues and circulars; student yearbooks; anniversary publications and histories; brochures; programs; newsletters; commencement programs; addresses; certificates of incorporation and articles of association; annual reports; photographs; report cards; diplomas; and alumni directories and publications.
The collection also includes one volume titled Souvenir of Our Public Schools, Brooklyn N.Y., which includes school staff listings, portraits of principals, and photographs of public school buildings in Brooklyn, dating from 1892.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Series 1 consists of general material regarding education and schools in Brooklyn. Series 2 is arranged into sub-series alphabetically by school name. Within each school sub-series, materials are listed chronologically.
Separated Materials
Upon reprocessing in 2023, materials from schools with their own dedicated composite collections at CBH were removed to those collections (see Related Materials note). Excessive duplicates were discarded, along with news clippings from periodicals available elsewhere.
Alumnae and alumni; Alumni directories; Annual reports; Brochures; College students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls -- Education (Primary) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls -- Education (Secondary) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls' schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; High school students -- New York (State) -- New York; Histories; Music education; Newsletters; Programs (documents); Publications; School yearbooks; Student publications; Student life and customs -- New York (State) -- New York; Students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Autograph albums; Brooklyn Teachers Association; New York City Technical College; St. John's University (New York, N.Y.); Union Missionary Training Institute; Caldwell Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Shore Road Academy (New York, N.Y.); Bryant & Stratton Business College; Columbian Institute and Kindergarten (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 35 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Colby Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Alexander Hamilton Vocational High School (New York. N.Y.); Grammar School 35 (New York, N.Y.); Commercial High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); De Severinus Academy of Fine and Applied Art (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Latin School for Boys; East Midwood Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Nassau Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Normal School for Physical Training; Trinity School (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Hill School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Joseph's College for Women (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Music School; Misses Peck School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Music School Settlement (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Roosa School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Post-Graduate Medical School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Catherine's Hall (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Preparatory School; South Brooklyn Female Seminary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Michael's Diocesan High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); College Grammar School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Harrison and Ranney's English and French Boarding and Day School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Hall's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Heffley School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Whitcomb's French, English, and German Day School for Young Ladies and Children; Harvey's Select School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); School District 15 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Round's School for Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hebrew Educational Society of Brooklyn; Miss Katherine L. Maltby's Home and School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kingsborough Community College; Long Island Business College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Misses Crawford's School for Boys and Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lafayette Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lafayette High School (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lockwood's New Academy; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Eastern District High School; Master School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Van Doren's Institute for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Froebel Academy; Walt Whitman School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Groschel Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Dudley's Seminary for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Greenleaf Female Institute; Brooklyn Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies; Brooklyn College of Pharmacy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Law School; Brooklyn Juvenile High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights Seminary; Bedford Heights Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brevoort School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Community-Woodward School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Auburn Academy and Educational Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Academy of the Visitation (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Abraham Lincoln High School (New York, N.Y.); Bay Ridge High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Evening High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn High school of Women's Garment Trades; Brooklyn Technical High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Catherine McAuley Commercial High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Cathedral College of the Immaculate Conception; C.F. Young School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Education in Brooklyn
  - Brooklyn Teachers Association, 1910-1926
    - Brooklyn Teacher newsletter, 1926, 1962 (Box 1)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Original is extremely fragile. Researchers should use the provided preservation photocopy.
    - Memorial Fund at Brooklyn Public Library, 1952-1964 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Correspondence, memos, and other documents related to the Brooklyn Teachers Association memorial fund at Brooklyn Public Library.
    - Annual reports, 1910-1914, 1923-1926 (Box 1)
  - School District 15
    - Focus on Fifteen newsletter, 1969 March-June (Box 1)
  - General school and education materials
    - City Superintendent of Schools annual reports, 1848, 1856, 1871, 1912-1913, 1916 (Box 1)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Microfiche versions are available in the library (1848, 1856, and 1871, Microfiche 40; 1912-1913, Microfiche 55).
      The 1848 and 1871 reports are extremely fragile. Researchers should use the microfiche versions whenever possible.
      Related Materials
      Microfiche versions of several other years are available in the library. See Microfiche 40.
    - Blank Brooklyn public school certificate, circa 1850s (Box 1)
    - Report of the Board of Education to the Common Council, 1853 (Box 1)
      A microfiche version is available in the library (Microfiche 42).
      This item is in fragile condition. Researchers should use the microfiche whenever possible.
    - Manual of the Board of Education, City of Brooklyn, 1856, 1860 (Box 1)
    - Names of Teachers in the Public Schools...of Kings County, NY, 1886 (Box 1)
    - Course of Study for the Public Schools of the City of Brooklyn, 1887 (Box 1)
      A microfiche version is available in the library (Microfiche 52).
      The original item is in poor condition. Researchers should use the microfiche whenever possible.
    - Clippings scrapbook, 1888-1893, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Souvenir of Our Public Schools, Brooklyn N.Y., 1892 (Box 1)
      Published by the New York State Office of Superintendent of Public Instruction. Includes school staff listings, portraits of principals, and photographs of public school buildings in Brooklyn.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Constance Delio.
    - Course of Study in Grammar Grades, 1897 (Box 1)
      A microfiche version is available in the library (Microfiche 49).
      This item is in porr condition. Researchers should use the microfiche version whenever possible.
    - Course of Study for the Vacation Schools of Brooklyn, 1900 (Box 1)
      A microfiche version is available in the library (Microfiche 46).
    - Course of Study for High Schools, 1905, 1908 (Box 1)
    - High School Examination - English, 1921 (Box 1)
    - Public Hearings on the Proposed Plan for a Community School District System in New York City, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Directory of the Public High Schools of the City of New York, 1969-1972 (Box 18)
      A microfiche version is available in the library (Microfiche 45).
    - Rights and Responsibilities of High School Students, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Catholic Schools Diocese of Brooklyn reports, 1962-1971 (Box 18)
    - Catholic Schools Diocese of Brooklyn directories, 1973-1990 (Box 18)
    - Board of Jewish Education school directories, 1978-1979, 1982 (Box 1)
    - The Eagle alumni newsletter, 1987 (Box 1)
    - New York City High School Poetry Contest Winners, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Board of Education annual school reports, 1993-1994 (Box 18)
      Includes Public School (P.S.) 3-399 (not inclusive), Intermediate School (I.S.) 14-394 (not inclusive), Harry Van Arsdale Junior High School (J.H.S.), J.H.S. 50, and high schools Brooklyn Technical, Redirection, Pacific and Street Academy.
    - New York City Public Schools Guide for Parents and Families, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - NYC Public Schools Admission Guide, 2023 (Box 18)
- Series 2: Individual schools
  - Abraham Lincoln High School
    See also the 1981 inter-school Sing program in the Midwood High School folder.
    - Landmark yearbook, 1935-1989 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      June 1935, June 1936, 1937, January 1938, June 1942, June 1944, June 1949, 1989
      The June 1937 yearbook was a transfer from Massapequa Library.
    - Commencement invitation and senior promenade ticket, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Commencement program, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Iris Abramson commencement program, diploma, and honor card, 1942 (Box 2)
      Gift of Linda and Marcy Chelmow, 2025.
      There is a copy of Abramson's senior photo in the collection's accession file. See also Abramson's materials under J.H.S. 228 David J. Boody and Brooklyn College.
    - 25th anniversary publication, 1945 (Box 2)
    - 46/50 publication, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Honor card, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Florida Alumni Chapter reunion programs, 1997, 2001 (Box 2)
      Gift of Mindy Turkenitz.
  - Academy for Environmental Leadership
    - Yearbook, 2010-2012, 2014 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Academy of Saint Francis Xavier
    - Prospectus, circa late 1800s (Box 2)
  - Academy of the Visitation
    - Catalogs, 1881-1882, 1891-1892 (Box 2)
  - Adelphi College
    - Event programs, 1909-1915 (Box 2)
  - Adelphi University
    - Library event materials, 1971, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Centennial calendar of events, 1995 Fall (Box 2)
  - Alexander Hamilton Junior High School
    - Ledger yearbook, June 1929, 1937 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Alexander Hamilton Vocational High School
    - Commencement program and invitation, 1947 (Box 2)
      Biographical / Historical
      This is a separate institution from The Commercial High School/Alexander Hamilton High School, which closed in 1942.
    - Technician yearbook, 1947-1950 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      June 1947, January & June 1948, June 1950
  - All Saints Commercial High School
    - Excelsior yearbook, 1948, 1949, 1959, 1967 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - American Institute of Architects, Brooklyn chapter
    - Yearbook, 1908 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Andrew Jackson High School
    - Basketball schedule, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
      Advertisement for Brooklyn Academy on verso.
  - Auburn Academy
    - Catalog, circa 1963 (Box 2)
  - Automotive High School
    - Crossroads yearbook, 1977 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Bay Ridge High School
    - Assembly song book, 1912 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
    - Maroon and White literary magazine, 1920, 1927, 1930, 1936 (Box 2)
      1920 and 1927 issues were the gift of Regina O'Grady-LeShane.
      The 1930 issue came with a clipping about alum Edith Bjorkman.
    - Commencement program, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Fabric pennant, "B.R.H.S.", circa early 20th century (Folder Flat File)
    - Maroon and White yearbook, 1941-1964 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      1946 copy gift of Joanne Canapary Stopka.
      January & June 1941, January 1942, 1944, May & December 1945, 1946, February & June 1947, January & June 1949, 19621964. 1944, 1945, 1963 & 1964 are art and literary supplements to the yearbook, not the yearbook proper.
  - Bedford Heights Institute
    - Promotional booklet, 1889-1890 (Box 2)
  - Bedford Institute
    - Receipt, 1878 (Box 2)
      Room rental to Miss M.T. Purdy, principal.
    - Catalogs, 1882-1883, 1889-1890, 1893-1897, 1898-1904, 1905-1915, 1916-1917, 1918-1933, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Berkeley Carroll (Street) School
    - Promotional flyers, circa 1980s (Box 2)
    - Bulletin, 1984, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Lion/The Berkeley Lion yearbook, 1985-1987 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
    - Yearbooks, 1989-2013 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      What a Shape We're In, 1989; The Big Picture, 1990; Fresh Perspectives, 1992; All The Pieces Fit, 1993; Think, Out Loud, 1994; Connections, 1996; The Sky's the Limit, 1998; Millenium, 2000; Defining Us, 2001; Good Times, 2002; A Work in Progress, 2003; Metamorphosis, 2006; Sui Generis, 2007; Transitions, 2008; Express Yourself, 2009; Filling the Blanks, 2013
    - Magazine, 2015 (Box 2)
  - Berkeley Institute
    - Catalogs, 1890-1891, 1898-1899 (Box 2)
    - Promotional booklet, pamphlet and announcement of changes, circa 1896-1897 (Box 2)
    - Berkeleydian literary magazine, November 1910 - June 1911 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      Monthly issues in this time span, bound together in one volume.
    - Event programs, 1932, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Yearbooks, 1942-1961 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      1945 and 1946 copies were the gift of Harold J. Manson, 1957.
      1942, 1945, 1946, 1948, 1956, 1958-1961
    - Promotional booklets, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - 75th anniversary publication, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Lion/The Berkeley Lion yearbook, 1965, 1974, 1977, 1979, 1981 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Bishop Ford (Central Catholic) High School
    - Commencement program, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Pagoda yearbook, 1980-2013 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      1980-1985, 1987, 1988, 1991, 1993, 1994, 1996, 1997, 1999, 20012013
    - Video yearbooks, 2000-2001, 2006-2011 (Box 13)
  - Bishop Kearney High School
    - Commencement program, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Bishop Loughlin Memorial High School
    - Purple and Gold student handbook, circa 1945 (Box 2)
    - Loughlinite yearbook, June 1946, 1949, 1954-1957, 1960 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
    - Photograph of alumni, circa 1980s (Box 2)
      Photograph includes Rudy Giuliani, who graduated from Bishop Loughlin in 1961.
  - Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School
    - Class Day program, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Commencement program, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Photographic postcard set, circa 1947; Barone, Rita G., -2021 (Box 2)
      These black and white postcards depict the school building with both exterior and interior views.
      Barone, Rita G., -2021
    - Laurel magazine, 1947-1949; Barone, Rita G., -2021 (Box 2)
  - Boro Hall Academy
    - Advertising blotters, circa 1940s (Box 2)
  - Boys and Girls High School
    - Students' Centennial Reader, 1979 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Boys High School
    - Red and Black yearbook, 1899-1928 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      1899-1901, 1908, 1909-1910, 1912, 1916, June 1928
    - Senior Recorder yearbook, 1935-1964 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      January 1935, June 1937, June 1941, June 1943, January 1950, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1964
    - Paragon yearbook, 1962 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  - Brevoort School
    - Catalog, 1898-1899 (Box 2)
  - Brooklyn Academy
    See advertisement for this school on verso of Andrew Jackson High School basketball schedule.
    - Commencement program, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Brooklyn Business School
    - Promotional pamphlet, circa early 1900s (Box 2)
  - Brooklyn Central School
    - Commencement programs and ticket, 1882-1890 (Box 3)
    - Catalog, 1886 (Box 3)
    - Astronomy notebook, 1888 (Box 3)
    - Fiftieth anniversary program, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn College
    - Broeklundian yearbook, 1933-1994 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      The 1962 issue is water damaged and the first section of the volume is unreadable as a result.
      1933-1938, 1940-1946, 1948, 1950-1954, 1962, 1994
    - Iris Abramson diploma, 1949 (Box 3)
      See also Abramson's materials under J.H.S. 228 David J. Boody and Abraham Lincoln High School.
    - Alumni Today, 2010 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
      Gift of Doris Berlin and Mindy Berlin Turkenitz.
  - Brooklyn College of Pharmacy
    - Catalog, 1894-1895 (Box 3)
    - Commencement materials, 1894, 1906, 1913 (Box 3)
    - Matriculation ticket, 1895 (Box 3)
    - Crimson and Gold yearbook, 1923 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
    - Fiftieth anniversary booklet, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute
    - Report cards, 1887-1890 (Box 14)
      Bound into a volume with other school ephemera.
  - Brooklyn Commercial Preparatory School
    - Promotional postcard, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn Community-Woodward School
    - Promotional materials, 1930, 1950s (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - Event materials, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Rostrum, 1965 Spring (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn Conservatory of Music
    - 25th anniversary booklet, 1922 (Box 3)
    - Event materials, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn Engineering Institute
    - Promotional booklet, circa 1930s (Box 3)
  - Brooklyn Evening High School
    - Evening Star yearbook, 1914-1916 (Volume Library gallery shelf)